Finding Aid for C. L. Franklin Papers 1957-1991
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
C. L. Franklin Papers 1957-1991, 1963-1984
Franklin, C. L. (Clarence LaVaughn), 1915-1984.
1 phonograph records
1 oversize folders
0.7 linear feet
Detroit African American clergyman and civil rights activist. Papers accumulated by Franklin's daughter, Erma Franklin, relating to the life and career of her father; include biographical information, transcripts of oral interviews; scattered sermons and correspondence, including letters from daughter Aretha and from Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr.; topical files about his church and civil rights activities; and photographs
99100 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
Erma Franklin (donor no. 8904 ), daughter of C. L. Franklin, allowed the library to make copies of Franklin materials in her possession. The copies were made in October 1999. Additions were received in 2004.
The collection is open for research.
C.L. Franklin was a nationally known African American clergyman, active in the civil right movement, and longtime pastor of New Bethel Baptist Church in Detroit, Michigan. He was born Clarence LaVaughn Franklin January 22, 1915 in Sunflower County, Mississippi. While a teenager, he started preaching in rural churches in Mississippi. In 1938, he went to Memphis to become pastor of New Salem Baptist Church. In Memphis, he also attended the Howe School of Religion and LeMoyne College. He later moved to a Baptist church in Buffalo, New York, and while there he took courses at the University of Buffalo.
In 1946, Franklin moved to Detroit where he founded New Bethel Baptist Church. In 1952, his wife Barbara died leaving Franklin to raise their five children: Erma, Carolyn, Aretha, Cecil, and Vaughn.
Franklin gained renown as a preacher whose oratorical skills were responsible in part for the great growth in New Bethel's membership over the next three decades. Franklin's ministry also included radio broadcasts and many of his messages were made available through commercially produced records. Franklin also achieved recognition outside of his own congregation. When preaching in other churches, Franklin often took his daughter Aretha with him. Her talent as a gifted gospel singer reflected on Franklin and the fame of his ministry grew.
Throughout his life, Franklin involved himself politically. He was ever mindful of the needs of both his congregation and of the wider African American community. He was active in civil rights issues and demonstrations and was vocal in his opposition to racism. In 1963, he help to organize and enlist support for the Freedom March led by Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr. down Woodward Avenue in Detroit. The march, which drew more than 125,000 participants, was claimed by some as the prototype of King's march in Washington later in the summer of that same year. A few years later, in 1969, Franklin rented his church to the Republic of New Africa, a militant African American separatist organization. While this meeting was in progress, police and bystanders outside the church exchanged gun fire. One policeman was killed. Subsequently, police stormed the church and arrested 142 individuals all of whom were later released when it was found that their arrests were made improperly. Not all of his congregation were pleased that their pastor had opened the church to this group, but Franklin was forthright in his belief that all groups should be given the opportunity to present their views.
In 1979, Franklin confronted burglars who had broken into his home. Franklin was shot twice and went into a coma that would last more than five years. He died July 27, 1984.
The C. L. Franklin collection is a small but significant accumulation of materials relating to the life and career of this Detroit-based clergyman. Although the collection dates from the mid-1950s, most of the materials fall within the period of 1963 to 1984. The collection is comprised of photocopies and copyprints of materials made available to the library by Erma Franklin. The importance of the collection is for the sampling of Franklin sermons that have been preserved, for the scattered documentation of the important March of Freedom that took place in Detroit in the summer of 1963, and for the copyprints made of photographs of Franklin, his family and his friends and professional associates. The collection has been arranged into five series: Biographical Information, Various Papers, Topical Files, Photographs, and Sound Recordings.
Subjects:
Afro-American clergy--Michigan--Detroit.; Afro-American churches--Michigan--Detroit.; Afro-Americans--Michigan--Detroit.; Baptists, Black--Michigan--Detroit.; Clergy--Michigan--Detroit.; Civil rights--Michigan--Detroit.; Detroit (Mich.)--Church history.; Detroit (Mich.)--Race relations.; Franklin, Aretha.; Franklin, C. L. (Clarence LaVaughn), 1915-1984.; Franklin, Erma.; New Bethel Baptist Church (Detroit, Mich.); Sermons.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Belafonte, Harry, 1927-; Churches--Michigan--Detroit.; Detroit (Mich.)--Churches.; Franklin, Aretha.; Franklin, C. L. (Clarence LaVaughn), 1915-1984.; Jones Prophet.; King, Martin Luther, Jr.; King, Coretta Scott, 1927-2006; Jackson, Mahalia, 1911-1972.; New Bethel Baptist Church (Detroit, Mich.); Parades & processions--Michigan--Detroit.; Powell, Adam Clayton, 1908-1972.; St. Marie, Buffy.
Contributors:
King, Martin Luther, Jr., 1929-1968.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Biographical Information
  Biographical Information consists of articles, clippings, and collected material on the life of C. L. Franklin. Of most significance are the transcripts of oral interviews with Franklin conducted by his biographer, Jeff Titon. These interviews were made in 1976 and 1977 and contain excellent information about Franklin's life. Also included here are transcripts made by Titon of several of Franklin's sermons.
  - Summary information and articles (Box 1)
  - Clippings (largely obituaries) (Box 1)
  - Memorial service programs 1984 (Box 1)
  - Jeff Titon (student of CLF life and preaching)
    - Article: "Reverend C.L. Franklin; Black-American Preacher Poet" (from Folklife Annual 1987), 1987 (Box 1)
    - Transcript of interview with CLF February 27, 1976, October 5, 1977 (Box 1)
      (includes correspondence related to the interviews and to Titon's book)
    - Transcripts of CLF sermons 1977, 6 items (Box 1)
- Various Papers
  Various Papers is the heading for the miscellanea of correspondence, sermons, other writings, and other documents preserved by C. L. Franklin and his family.
  - Correspondence 1957-1991, undated (Box 1)
  - Sermons, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Clippings (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Topical Files
  The Topical Files series contains information about the March of Freedom in 1963, about New Bethel Baptist Church, a scattering of papers about Franklin's civil rights activities, about the care given him following his shooting, and the efforts made to memorialize him.
  - Detroit Council for Human Rights 1963 (Box 1)
  - Evangelistic Board, National Baptist Convention, USA mid-winter board meetings 1961 (Box 1)
  - Franklin. C.L. Franklin Memorial Committee/C.L. Franklin Medical Trust Fund 1983-1992 (Box 1)
  - Franklin family information (Box 1)
  - International Afro Musical and Cultural Festival (Box 1)
  - King. Martin Luther King, Jr. (letters) 1963 (Box 1)
  - March of Freedom in Detroit June 1963 (Box 1)
  - March of Freedom in Detroit (later commemorations) (Box 1)
  - Metropolitan Civic League for Legal Action (Box 1)
  - New Bethel Baptist Church (publications, etc.) (Box 1)
  - "An Open Letter to White America" 1967 (Box 1)
    (re Detroit riot)
  - "Soul Bowl '69'" 1969 (Box 1)
- Photographs
  Photographs is made up of copyprints (with some originals) of photographs in the possession of Erma Franklin and photocopies of images for which copyprints were not made. The photographs include portraits of Franklin and his family, particularly his daughter Aretha, photos of Franklin as participant in the 1963 March of Freedom and with other notables, such as Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr., Adam Clayton Powell, and Mahalia Jackson. Other photographs are of the New Bethel Baptist Church, a group photograph that includes Detroit preacher Prophet Jones, and group photographs of Franklin and his children.
  - Portraits of CLF (Box 1)
  - CLF with children (Box 1)
  - Aretha Franklin (Aretha Franklin Day) 1968 (Box 1)
    (images of Aretha Franklin on stage with father and with Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr.; also backstage photos of AF with Harry Belafonte and Buffy St. Marie)
  - CLF with other dignitaries (Box 1)
    (include Martin Luther King, Coretta Scott King, Adam Clayton Powell, and Mahalia Jackson)
  - March of Freedom in Detroit June 1963 (Box 1)
  - New Bethel Baptist Church (Box 1)
    (exterior view and interior views of church during services)
  - Various (Box 1)
    (include group photo with Prophet Jones in white coat)
  - Photocopies of photographs for which copyprints were not made, 2 folders (Box 1)
- Sound recording
  Sound Recordings consists of a 78 rpm sound disc featuring C. L. Franklin and choir singing two hymns. The library has also purchased sound cassette copies of Rev. Franklin preaching. These have been separately cataloged and located.
  - Phonograph record: Rev. C.L. Franklin and Congregation sings (65-A) "I love the Lord" (65-B) "Heard the Voice of Jesus" J-V-B Recording Co., 1 phonograph records 78 rpm (Box 1)
    (located in phonograph disk collection)
  - C.L. Franklin Preaching, "Show to show thyself approved unto God" and Silver and Gold have I none but such as I have thee...", 1 audiocassettes (Box 1)
  - Funeral Service for Rev. C.L. Franklin, 3 audiocassettes (Box 1)